

Senior Researcher | Department of Computer Science | ETH Zurich □+41 764999105 | **Si.liu@inf.ethz.ch**

Research Interests

Si Liu's research interests encompass formal methods (FM), software engineering (SE), and distributed systems, with a particular emphasis on applying FM and SE techniques to build reliable, secure, and efficient distributed systems. His current work focuses on verifying and validating the designs & deployments of databases and DNS, addressing both qualitative (e.g., reliability and security) & quantitative (e.g., availability and scalability) aspects. He has also recently developed an interest in the verification of AI systems.

Education ___

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

PhD in Computer Science Aug. 2012 - May 2019

• Advisor: Prof. Dr. Jose Meseguer

East China Normal University (ECNU)

MASTER IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Sep. 2009 - May 2012

East China Normal University (ECNU)

BACHELOR IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING Sep. 2005 - Jun. 2009

Professional Experience _____

| May 2023 – Present | Senior Researcher (Deutsch: Oberassistent), ETH Zurich |
|-----------------------|--|
| Aug. 2019 – May 2023 | Postdoc Researcher, ETH Zurich |
| Sep. 2014 – Sep. 2017 | Research Assistant, Assured Cloud Computing Center, UIUC |
| Jun. 2011 – Aug. 2011 | Research Intern, National Cyber-Physical Systems Camp, USTC |
| Sep. 2009 – May 2012 | Research Assistant, Danish-Chinese Research Center, ECNU |
| May 2008 – Feb. 2009 | Software Engineering Intern , Dept. of Talent House, Hewlett-Packard Co. Ltd. |

Awards & Honors

2024 Career Seed Award, ETH Zurich

CHF 30,000

- 2024 The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich
- 2023 The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich
- 2012 Outstanding Graduate Award (Ranked 1st), East China Normal University
- 2011 Excellent Student Award (Ranked 1st), East China Normal University

Publications _____

• FM/SE x DATABASES

Under Submission:

- [-'25] Zhiheng Cai, Si Liu*, Hengfeng Wei. Uniso: A Unified Framework for Efficiently Checking Database Isolation Guarantees.
- [-'25] Jiang Xiao[†], **Si Liu**, Hengfeng Wei. Boosting Database Isolation Checking via Mini-Transactions
- [-'25] Zijing Yin[†], Si Liu, David Basin. Stressing Graph Databases with Synthesized Complex Queries

^{*} I contributed equally as a co-first author † indicates the students I supervised

Under Revision:

[VLDB'25] Shabnam Ghasemirad[†], **Si Liu**, Luca Multazzu, Christoph Sprenger, David Basin. VerIso: Verifiable Isolation Guarantees for Database Transactions

Published:

- [OOPSLA'24] Si Liu, Long Gu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. Plume: Efficient and Complete Black-box Checking of Weak Isolation Levels
- [SIGMOD'24] Si Liu, Luca Multazzu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Distributed Transactions
 - [VLDB'24] Long Gu[†], Si Liu, Tiancheng Xing, Hengfeng Wei, Yuxing Chen, David Basin. IsoVista: Black-box Checking Database Isolation Guarantees. **Demo Track**
 - [VLDB'23] Kaile Huang, Si Liu*, Zhenge Chen, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin, Haixiang Li, Anqun Pan. Efficient Black-box Checking of Snapshot Isolation in Databases
 - [OSDI'23] Zu-Ming Jiang, Si Liu, Manuel Rigger, Zhendong Su. Detecting Transactional Bugs in Database Engines via Graph-Based Oracle Construction
- [OOPSLA'22] Si Liu, Jose Meseguer, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, David Basin. Bridging the Semantic Gap between Qualitative and Quantitative Models of Distributed Systems
- [TOSEM'22] Si Liu. All in One: Design, Verification, and Implementation of SNOW-Optimal Read Atomic Transactions

• FM x DNS (AND BEYOND)

Under Submission:

[-'25] Dhruv Nevatia[†], **Si Liu**, David Basin. Reachability Analysis of the Domain Name System

Published:

- [USENIX SEC'24] Huayi Duan, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, David Basin, Si Liu, Bernhard Tellenbach. CAMP: Compositional Amplification Attacks against DNS
 - [SIGCOMM'23] Si Liu, Huayi Duan, Lukas Heimes, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, David Basin. A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution
 - [NSDI'23] Huayi Duan, Fischer Ruben, Lou Jie, Si Liu, David Basin, Adrian Perrig. RHINE: Robust and Highperformance Internet Naming with E2E Authenticity
 - [CSF'22] Thilo Weghorn, Si Liu*, Christoph Sprenger, Adrian Perrig, David Basin. N-Tube: Formally Verified Secure Bandwidth Reservation in Path-Aware Internet Architectures
- [Book Chapter] David Basin, Tobias Klenze, Si Liu, Christoph Sprenger. Design-Level Verification in The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification. 2022
- [Book Chapter] Giacomo Giuliari, Markus Legner, Si Liu, Adrian Perrig, Thilo Weghorn, Marc Wyss. Extensions for the Data Plane in The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification. 2022

• FM/SE x AI

Under Submission:

[—'25] Shi Peng, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Chenyang Xu, Cheng Chen, Dapeng Zhi, Min Zhang. ATA: An Abstract-Train-Abstract Approach for Explanation-Friendly Deep Reinforcement Learning

Published:

- [CAV'24] Dapeng Zhi, Peixin Wang, Si Liu, Luke Ong, Min Zhang. Unifying Qualitative and Quantitative Safety Verification of DNN-Controlled Systems
- **[VMCAI'24]** Jiaxu Tian, Dapeng Zhi, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Guy Katz, Min Zhang. Taming Reachability Analysis of DNN-Controlled Systems via Abstraction-Based Training

- [NeurlPS'23] Jiaxu Tian, Dapeng Zhi, Si Liu, Peixin Wang, Cheng Chen, Min Zhang. Boosting Verification of Deep Reinforcement Learning via Piece-Wise Linear Decision Neural Networks
 - [CVPR'23] Zhaodi Zhang, Zhiyi Xue, Yang Chen, Si Liu, Yueling Zhang, Jing Liu, Min Zhang. Boosting Verified Training for Robust Image Classifications via Abstraction
 - [ISSTA'23] Zhiyi Xue, Si Liu, Zhaodi Zhang, Yiting Wu, Min Zhang. A Tale of Two Approximations: Tightening Over-Approximation for DNN Robustness Verification via Under-Approximation
 - [ASE'22] Zhaodi Zhang, Yiting Wu, Si Liu, Jing Liu, Min Zhang. Provably Tightest Linear Approximation for Robustness Verification of Sigmoid-like Neural Networks

PRIOR TO 2022:

- [TASE'21] Lei Liang, Si Liu. Exploring Design Alternatives for Replicated RAMP Transactions Using Maude
- [NFM'20] Si Liu, Atul Sandur, Jose Meseguer, Peter Olveczky, Qi Wang. Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs
- **[TACAS'19] Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, Qi Wang, Jose Meseguer. Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude.
- **[FAoC'19] Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Read Atomic Transactions with Prevention of Lost Updates: ROLA and Its Formal Analysis. *Formal Aspects of Computing*
 - [CCS'19] Qi Wang, Pubali Datta, Wei Yang, Si Liu, Carl Gunter, Adam Bates. Charting the Attack Surface of Trigger-Action IoT Platforms.
- [FASE'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Keshav Santhanam, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. ROLA: A New Distributed Transaction Protocol and Its Formal Analysis.
- [LITES'17] Si Liu, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Son Nguyen, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Leibniz Transactions on Embedded Systems*
- [ICFEM'17] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking.
- [**JLAMP'16**] **Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, José Meseguer. Modeling and Analyzing Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. *Journal of Logical and Algebraic Methods in Programming*
 - [SAC'16] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems.
- [QEST'15] Si Liu, Son Nguyen, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer.

 Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Nominated for Best Paper*.
- [ICFEM'14] Si Liu, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Stephen Skeirik, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude.
- [PRDC'14] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu and Yongxin Zhao. Reasoning about Group-Based Mobility in MANETs.
- [ComSIS'13] Xi Wu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Zheng Wang, Si Liu. Modeling and verifying the Ariadne protocol using process algebra. Computer Science and Information Systems Journal
 - [ECBS'12] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Lei Chen. Modeling and Verifying the Ariadne Protocol Using CSP.
 - [HASE'11] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective.
 - [TASE'11a] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks.
 - **[TASE'11b]** Mengying Wang, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, **Si Liu**. Modeling and Analyzing the μ TESLA Protocol Using CSP.
- [ICECCS'11] Yongxin Zhao, Yanhong Huang, Jifeng He, Si Liu. Formal Model of Interrupt Program from a Probabilistic Perspective.
 - [SSIRI'11] Si Liu, Xiaofeng Wu, Qin Li, Huibiao Zhu, Qian Wang. Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks.
 - [UTP'10] Qin Li, Yongxin Zhao, Xiaofeng Wu, Si Liu. Promoting Models.

WORKSHOP PAPERS

- [WRLA'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of the Walter Transactional Data Store.
 - [SSS'15] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. Formal analysis of Leader Election in MANETs Using Real-Time Maude.
- [WRLA'14] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude.
- [SSIRI'11] Han Zhu, Huibiao Zhu, Si Liu, Jian Guo. Towards Denotational Semantics for Verilog in PVS.

OTHER BOOK CHAPTERS

• Rakesh Bobba, Jon Grov, Indranil Gupta, **Si Liu**, José Meseguer, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Stephen Skeirik. Survivability: Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. 2018.

PHD THESIS

• Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign. 2019

Teaching Experience _____

| Fall 2024 | Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
|-------------|--|------------|
| Spring 2024 | Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2023 | Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Spring 2023 | Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2022 | Information Systems for Engineers, Head Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Spring 2022 | Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2021 | Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Spring 2021 | Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2020 | Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Spring 2020 | Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2019 | Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant | ETH Zurich |
| Fall 2016 | Distributed Systems, Teaching Assistant | UIUC |
| Fall 2011 | Process Algebra, Teaching Assistant | ECNU |
| Spring 2011 | Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant | ECNU |
| Fall 2010 | Discrete Mathematics, Teaching Assistant | ECNU |
| Spring 2010 | Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant | ECNU |

Mentoring _____

PhD students

- Dhruv Nevatia (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (co-supervised with Dr. Christoph Sprenger and Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Zijing Yin (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Ziwei Zhou (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Shi Peng (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Zhaodi Zhang (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang; first employment: Chengdu Education Research Institute), ECNU

Graduate students

- Theodor Moroianu, ETH Zurich
- Yunxin Sun, ETH Zurich
- Yufei Zhang, ETH Zurich
- Rolando Grave de Peralta, ETH Zurich
- Zhou Zhou, ECNU
- Long Gu, Nanjing University
- Qiuhuan Xiong, Nanjing University
- Luca Multazz (first employment: SICPA), ETH Zurich
 - * honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "NOCS-Optimal Distributed Transactions and Beyon" (top 2.5%)
- Lukas Heimes (first employment: SBB CFF FFS), ETH Zurich
 - * honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution" (top 2.5%)
- Jodok Vieli (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Marco Bearzi (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (now PhD at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich
- Jiang Xiao (first employment: Agricultural Bank of China), Nanjing University
- Jiaxu Tian (first employment: CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Zhiyi Xue (now PhD at ECNU), ECNU

Undergraduate students

- Tiancheng Xing (graduated, now Master at NUS), Nanjing University
- Zhiheng Cai (graduated, now PhD at Tsinghua University), Nanjing University
- Long Gu (graduated, now Master at Nanjing University), Nanjing University
- Zhenge Chen (graduated, now Master at UCSD), Nanjing University
- Teng Wang (graduated), Nanjing University
- Zhou Zhou (graduated, now Master at ECNU), ECNU
- Ziwei Zhou (graduated, now PhD at ECNU), ECNU
- Ruiyang Liu (graduated, now Master at JHU), ECNU
- Lei Liang (graduated, now at CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Plamen Stefanov (graduated, now Master at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich
- Keshav Santhanam (graduated, now PhD at Stanford University), UIUC

Professional Activities

• Program Committee Member: NSDI'25, ICFEM'24, ICFEM'23

- Journal Reviewer: JLAMP
- **Sub-Reviewer:** ICFEM'22, FM'21, FM'18, ICFEM'16, FASE'14, ICFEM'14, ICFEM'13, ICFEM'12, TASE'12, ICFEM'11, TASE'11, ICFEM'10
- Dagstuhl Seminar: "Ensuring the Reliability and Robustness of Database Management Systems (21442)"
 2021 (participant)
- **Grant Proposal:** preparing proposal for NSF CNS 1409416 (\$584,000, 2014 2017), Availability-Consistency Tradeoffs in Key-Value and NoSQL Storage Systems

Talks & Presentations ___

- NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Distributed Transactions. SIGMOD'24, Santiago, Chile, 2024.
- Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs. NFM'20, Virtual, 2020.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University Paris Diderot, France, 2019.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. ETH Zurich, Switzerland, 2019.
- Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. TACAS'19, Prague, Czech Republic, 2019.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking. ICFEM'17, Xi'an, China, 2017.
- Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. Huawei, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for the RAMP Transaction System Through Statistical Model Checking. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. SAC'16, Pisa, Italy, 2016.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2016.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. QEST'15, Madrid, Spain, 2015.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2015.
- A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. WRLA'14, Grenoble, France, 2014.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2014.
- A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective. HASE'11, Boca Raton, USA, 2011
- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. University of Science and Technology of China, Suzhou, China, 2011.
- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. TASE'11, Xi'an, China, 2011.
- Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks. SSIRI'11, Jeju Island, Korea, 2011.